Saeed Iqbal Deep Learning Scientist

github.com/saeediqbal linkedin.com/in/saeed-iqbal-khattak

RESEARCH INTEREST

My research interests lie primarily in working with deep learning methodologies for integrating and analyzing extensive collections of multi-modal medical images and object detection/tracking. I began my research career back in 2009 in security on smartphone platforms, specifically Android and was working on usage control and attestation of this immensely popular smartphone software stack. During graduation, I completed and delivered some machine learning-based applications. Subsequently, my interests are developing towards machine learning and deep learning models to aid medical image analysis for tumor detection. I have hands-on experience working with radiology images and deep learning techniques, Convolutional Neural Networks (CNN), Recurrent Neural Networks (RNN), time-series analysis, feature extraction, reinforcement and supervised/unsupervised learning. My Ph.D. research also lies in medical imaging analysis using deep learning techniques and I plan to continue my post-doc research in the same area.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy (Computer Science), University of Central Punjab, Pakistan	MAY 2023
Master of Science (Computer Science), National University of Computer & Emerging Sciences, Pakistan	DEC 2012
Bachelor of Information Technology (Honours), Punjab University College of Information Technology, Pakistan	OCT 2007
Higher Secondary School Certificate, BISE, Lahore, Pakistan	JUL 2003
Secondary School Certificate. BISE. Peshawar, Pakistan	JUN 2000

PUBLICATION

- Iqbal, S., Qureshi, A. N., Aurangzeb, K., & Javeed, K. (2023). Privacy-Preserving Collaborative AI for Distributed Deep Learning with Cross-sectional Data, IEEE 5th International Conference on Bio-engineering for Smart Technologies (BioSMART), Paris, France, doi:10.1109/BioSMART58455.2023.10162106, 07-09 June 2023, IEEE.
- Iqbal, S., Qureshi, A. N., Li, J., Arshad, I., & Mahmood, T. (2022). Dynamic Learning for Imbalance Data in Learning Chest X-Ray and CT Images. HELIYON, (2023), doi:10.1016/j.heliyon.2023.e16807, impact factor: 3.776, Cell Press & Science Direct, Elsevier.
- Iqbal, S., Qureshi, A. N., Li, J., & Mahmood, T. (2023). On the Analyses of Medical Images using Traditional Machine Learning Techniques and Convolutional Neural Networks, Springer Archives of Computational Methods in Engineering, doi:10.1007/s11831-023-09899-9, impact factor:8.171, Springer Nature.
- Iqbal, S., Qureshi, A. N., Ullah, A., Li, J., & Mahmood, T. (2022). Improving the Robustness and Quality of Biomedical CNN Models through Adaptive Hyperparameter Tuning. Applied Sciences, 12(22), 11870, doi:10.3390/app122211870, impact factor: 2.838, MDPI.
- ✓ Iqbal, S., & Qureshi, A. N. (2022). "A heteromorphous deep CNN framework for Medical Image Segmentation using Local Binary Pattern", pp:63466-63480, doi:10.1109/ACCESS.2022.3183331, impact factor: 3.367 IEEE Access.
- Iqbal, S., & Qureshi, A. N. "Deep-Hist: Breast cancer diagnosis through histopathological images using convolution neural network", Journal of Intelligent & Fuzzy Systems, pp: 1347-1364, doi: 10.3233/JIFS-213158, impact factor: 1.739, IOS Press.
- Iqbal, S., Qureshi, A. N., & Mustafa, G. (2022). "Hybridization of CNN with LBP for Classification of Melanoma Images", CMC-COMPUTERS MATERIALS & CONTINUA, vol. 71(3), pp: 4915-4939, doi:10.32604/cmc.2022.023178, impact factor: 3.860, Tech Science, Press.
- Shaheen, M., Ahsan, A., & Iqbal, S. (2021). "Data Mining of Scientometrics for Classifying Science Journals". Intelligent Automation and Soft Computing, vol.28(3), pp: 873-885, doi:10.32604/iasc.2021.016622, impact factor: 1.647, Tech Science, Press.
- Iqbal, S., Qureshi, A. N., & Akter, M. (2019, September). "Using Local Binary Patterns and Convolutional Neural Networks for Melanoma Detection". In Proceedings of SAI Intelligent Systems Conference, London, United Kingdom, (pp. 782-789), doi:10.1007/978-3-030-29513-4 58, Springer, Cham.
- Iqbal, S., Qureshi, A. N., & Lodhi, A. M. (2018, September). "Content based video retrieval using convolutional neural network". In Proceedings of SAI Intelligent Systems Conference, London United Kingdom, (pp. 170-186), doi:10.1007/978-3-030-01054-6_12, Springer, Cham.
- Iqbal, S., Choudhry, I. A., & Shabbir, K. (2016). "Verification of Android Permission Extension Framework using SPF and JPF". International Journal of Computer Science and Information Security, vol. 14(10), 340.
- Iqbal, S., and Muhammad Shaheen. "A machine learning based method for optimal journal classification." In Internet Technology and Secured Transactions (ICITST), 2013 8th International Conference for, pp. 259-264, doi:10.1109/ICITST.2013.6750202, IEEE.
- Shaheen, M., & Iqbal, S. (2013, December). Labeled clustering a unique method to label unsupervised classes. In 8th International Conference for Internet Technology and Secured Transactions (ICITST-2013) (pp. 210-214), doi:10.1109/ICITST.2013.6750193, IEEE.
- ✓ Iqbal, S., Shah, S. U., Nauman, M., & Amin, M. (2013, August). Extending java pathfinder (JPF) with property classes for verification of android permission extension framework. In 2013 IEEE 3rd International Conference on System Engineering and Technology (pp. 15-20), doi: 10.1109/ICSEngT.2013.6650135, IEEE.

Saeed Iqbal Deep Learning Scientist

github.com/saeediqbal linkedin.com/in/saeed-iqbal-khattak

JUL 2013 - Present

Lahore, Pakistan

INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY & COPYRIGHT

1. **Holistic Campus Security** optimized detection/tracking system using Deep Learning with commodity hardware (PTZ cameras) in real-time environment.

PUBLICATION IN PROGRESS

- Iqbal, S., Qureshi, A. N., Alhussein, M., Mustafa, G., Aurangzeb, K., Javeed, K., & Naqvi, R. A. (2023). Privacy-Preserving Collaborative AI for Distributed Deep Learning with Cross-sectional Data, Multimedia Tools and Applications, Springer, (2023) Under Review
- Iqbal, S., Qureshi, A. N., Alhussein, M., Mustafa, Choudhry, I.A., G., Aurangzeb, K., & Khan, T. M. (2023). A Fusion Approach for Modality Retrieval in Medical Image Analysis: Integrating Textural and Visual Features, Scientific Reports, Nature, (2023) Under Review.
- Iqbal, S., Qureshi, A. N., Li, J., & Mahmood, T. (2022). AD-CAM: A Model Agnostic Loss Function to Reduce Opacity of Convolutional Neural Networks - From Black Box to Glass Box. Expert Systems With Applications (ESWA), Elsevier, (2023), Under Review
- Iqbal, S., Qureshi, A. N., Alhussein, M., Mustafa, G., Aurangzeb, K., & Kadry, S. (2023). Ascertaining Effectiveness of Fusion of Handcrafted and Latent Semantic Features for Analyses of Medical Tomography Images. Knowledge-Based Systems (KBS), Elsevier, (2023), Under Review
- Iqbal, S., Qureshi, A. N., Aurangzeb, K., Alhussein, M., Haider, S. I., & Rida, I. (2023). AMIAC: Adaptive Medical Image Analyses and Classification, a Robust Self-Learning Framework. Neural Computing and Applications (NCAA), Springer, (2023), Under Review

RESEARCH PROJECT

- My Antenatal Monitoring Assistant (MAMA), Maternal and fetal health care is a global challenge in developed and developing countries. Complications occurring during pregnancy can result in the mother's and infant's death. The significant reasons associated with such adverse outcomes are the lifestyle of the mother as well as limited knowledge regarding pregnancies.
- Skin Cancer Detector, developing software that can detect skin cancer from images using computer vision without the painful and time-consuming process of laboratories and reduce the cost of laboratory tests.
- Capturing Human Action for Smart Vehicles, developing a system that will alert the driver on such scenarios by tracking eye movements, head movements, and gestures within specific time frames.
- Human Action Recognition System, optimized detection/tracking system using Deep Learning with commodity hardware (PTZ cameras) in real-time environment.
- **Breast Cancer Detection,** working on R&D of breast cancer to recognize cancer from images using computer vision and deep learning model with the help of PyTorch (fb.com) and Tensor flow (google.com)
- CMS for Graduate Student, developing a web-based software to store/managed Graduate Data according to NCEAC and HEC requirements.

EXPERIENCE

Researcher SEP 2022 - Present

Beijing Engineering Research Center for IoT Software and Systems, Beijing, China

* Responsible for collaborating and managing the research members in publishing research results and proposing projects in the areas of pertinent feature recognition, artificial intelligence, medical image analysis, health informatics, and biomedical signal processing. This includes actively participating in collaborative research efforts and preparing project proposals to secure funding for future research endeavors.

Assistant Professor
University of Central Punjab,

- * Samsung Innovation Campus course for undergraduate and graduate.
 - Taught the landscape of data science, and AI modeling with the foundation of mathematics, and deliver the basic concepts of probability and linear algebra using Python.
- * Designed and taught the following undergraduate Computer Science courses:
 - Object Oriented Programming (4 CHrs) (FALL 2022)
 - Programming for Big Data (3 CHrs) (SPRING 2022, 2021 & 2020, FALL 2021, 2020 & 2019)
 - Introduction to Computing (4 CHrs) (FALL 2021, 2020, 2019 & 2014, Spring 2015, 2014 and Summer 2014)

Saeed Igbal Deep Learning Scientist

github.com/saeediqbal linkedin.com/in/saeed-igbal-khattak

- Web Information Retrieval (3 CHrs) (FALL 2018, Summer 2018& 2017)
- Web Application Development (3 CHrs) (FALL 2018, 2016 & 2015, Summer 2017, Spring 2017)
- Introduction to DBMS (4 CHrs) (Spring 2019, 2018 & 2016, Summer 2016 & 2013, Fall 2015)
- Operating Systems (4 CHrs) (FALL & Spring 2013)
- Programming Fundamentals (4 CHrs) (FALL 2013)
- * Designed and taught the following graduate (MS. and Ph.D.) Computer Science and Data Science courses:
 - Tools and Techniques in Data Science (Spring 2023).
 - Research Methodology (FALL 2022).
- To encourage students' intrinsic motivation, teachers should give them meaningful and increasingly difficult learning opportunities, such as those that require them to explore themselves, ask questions, make decisions, set goals, organize their work, put it into practice, reflect on their progress, and take the initiative in their work.
- To get students involved in active, practical, and creative problem-based learning.
- * To give chances for students to acquire and apply contemporary technology, resources, and information to address challenges.
- * Coordination with BS students (both CS and SE) regarding timetable and course guidance (UNI/CS elective courses).
- * Student registrations, managing student dropout and withdrawal cases.
- * Managing and Controlling Midterm and Final Examination.
- Providing guidelines regarding exams (midterm and final), coordinating with IT staff to install and configure software/hardware, during examination, providing support and help to invigilators and students.

SEP 2009 - APR 2013 Lecturer HPS College (Govt), Hangu, KP

- * Design & taught basic Computer Science courses for B.Sc and F.Sc level.
 - * Weekly lectures to students enrolled in a programming language course and introductory physics course.
 - * Explained complex concepts in a small group setting; grade assignments and examinations.
 - * Held office hours for individual student discussion.

and prepare a work plan for a new project.

- * Responsible for 1-hr lecture and supervision of 3-hrs laboratory.
- * Won 2^{nd} prize in final evaluation.

Sr. Software Engineer **JAN 2006 - SEP 2009** Lahore, Pakistan

iSOFT Technology

* Investigate, analyze, design, develop and implement applications that support day-to-day operations, regarding technology

- improvements, upgrades and modifications. * To lead and manage a project team of technical engineers (including both designers and developers) in order to deliver
- project solutions on time and within budget. Novel application of sophisticated quantitative analysis and modeling techniques to new projects and analysis and Design
- * Development of algorithms for new projects and verifying those algorithms and responsible for the acquisition, setup, and administration of all hardware and software systems.

GRADUATE SUPERVISION

I supervised master's level students studying medical image analysis.

- ★ Diabetic Foot Ulcer Segmentation Using Context-Aware Hybrid Approach Laiga Imran L1S21MSCS0003
- Hybrid Approach of Feature Engineering and Convolutional Neural Network for Images Classification Izaz Ahmad –
- ★ Context-based Detection of Diabetic Retinopathy using Deep Learning Shahbaz Ali L1F21MSCS00053

ADVISING FINAL YEAR PROJECT

- ★ Content wise Data Management (2013 2015)
- ★ Computer based Emulator to Control Android Phone (CECAP) (2013-2015)
- ★ University level Plagiarism Detector (2013 2015)
- ★ iOS Game 3D Para-glider (2013 2015)
- ★ SMART EYE Portable Scanner (2013 2015)
- ★ Multiplayer Poker (2014 2015)
- * Safe Player (2015 2016)
- * Eligibility Finder (2015 2016)
- * Knockout Enemy (2015 2016)
- ★ Battle with Zombies (2014 2015)
- ★ Eligibility Finder (2015 2016)
- ★ FYP Evaluator (2016 2017)
- ★ ROAD TRAFFIC MONITORING SYSTEM USING COMPUTER VISION (2016 2017)
- ★ AD'S CAFE (2016 2017)
- ★ Content Wise Video Classification (2016 –2017)
- ★ Fraggie Notifier (2016 2017)
- ★ ORDEREASE (2017 2018)
- ★ HYREMEI (2017 2018)
- ★ UNDERSTANDING OF HUMAN ACTIONS FOR SMART VEHICLES (2017 2018)
- ★ SCHOOL ADVISOR (2017 2018)
- ★ GOCART (2017 2018)
- ★ SMART BOT (2017 2018)
- ★ RENT ADVISOR (2017 2018)
- ★ SKIN CANCER DETECTOR (2017 2018)
- ★ LEARNING BASED AUTOMATED HUMAN TRACKING SYSTEM (2017 2018)
- ★ AGRICULTURE IOT (2017 2018)
- ★ TEAM-X (2017 2018)
- ★ MOVEMENT DETECTION Human Action detection using deep learning (2018 2019)
- ★ SHIP DETECTION ship detection using deep learning with dataset SAR Images (2018 2019)
- ★ CANCER HISTOPHATHOLOGICAL IMAGE CLASSIFICATION BY DEEP LEARNING breast cancer detection using deep learning with BreakHis dataset(2018–2019)
- ★ KYN (KNOW YOUR NEIGHBOR) an android app to communicate with neighborhoods regarding societies problems (2018 –
- ★ APIFY a web development framework: it will help regarding different integration problem of different libraries and with apps. (2018 – 2019)
- ★ EASY PRESCRIPTION READER Often times we have prescriptions lying around our home and we want to check what the names of these medicines are but the writing is completely unreadable by a normal person except a physician or a pharmacy
- * Haroof-e-tahaji Letter Recognizer Our objective is to create a mobile app (iOS) that will capture an image and then digitized version of the document/image. We are covering basic Haroof-e-Tahajii letters that are 38 Letters. This will help developers to make different apps related to Urdu as translation apps, billboard, scanner (Urdu PDF), Urdu editing tools which will increase the level of Urdu language.
- * Real Time Object Finder
- * Banner Curve-Text Detection
- ★ Text-2-Image Generation
- ★ Object Localization

SKILLS

Deep Learning and Expert Level: Tensor flow, PyTorch, Keras, Open CV.

Computer Vision API: Intermediate Level: Google BigQurey, Tika, Jackrabbit, Nutch (Lucene & Solr)

Programming Language: Expert Level: Java, Python, C, C++, JavaScript, HTML, ŁTFX, AJAX, PHP, SQL, MySQL, Web Services, CSS

and XML (DTD, Schema, DOM)

Version Control & Software Configuration ManBeginner Level: Distributed Version Control System (DVCS), Mercurial/MQ, Git/StGit & VCS (RCS, CVS, SVN,

Beginner Level: Spark/Hadoop/Mapreduce (HBase, NoSQL (MongoDB, Cassandra), Mahout (Parallel

agement:

Software Verification:

Intermediate Level: Java Pathfinder (JPF), Simple PRomela Interpreter (SPIN) & NuSMV.

Cloud Computing Tech-

Clustering/Classification Techniques)

Mathematical optimization, Mathematical Modeling & MySQL **Quantitative Research:**

nology:

+92-333-9533493 saeediqbalkhattak@gmail.com

Saeed Iqbal Deep Learning Scientist

github.com/saeediqbal linkedin.com/in/saeed-iqbal-khattak

EDITORIAL SERVICES

Program Committee

Served on the Program Committee of the 7th International Conference on IT Convergence and Security (ICITCS 2017) – the leading conference on Trusted & Security technologies.

Served on the Program Committee of IEEE Symposium on Computer Applications & Industrial Electronics

- the leading conference on computing industry technologies

Journal and Conference Reviews Reviewed articles for several journals including IEEE ACCESS, Springer Archives of Computational Methods in Engineering, Applied Intelligence, SAGE Digital Health, Tech Science Computers, Materials & Continua, IOS Press Journal of Intelligent & Fuzzy Systems (JIFS) and Elsevier Computer Biology and Medicine

CERTIFICATES

Big Data and Hadoop, Udemy, Inc.	DEC 2016
Hadoop, MR, Hive and Spark, Udemy, Inc.	DEC 2016
Introduction to Python, <i>Udemy, Inc.</i>	DEC 2016
Introduction to the Biology of Cancer, Coursera, Inc.	NOV 2021

REFERENCES

Dr. Adnan N. Qureshi, University of Central Punjab, Pakistan

dranq@yahoo.com

Dr. Khursheed Aurangzeb, Department of Computer Science, College of Computer and Information Sciences,

King Saud University, Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

kaurangzeb@ksu.edu.sa

Dr. Mohammad Nauman, Department of Computer Science, Effat College of Engineering,

Effat University, Jeddah, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia

recluze@gmail.com